good evening everyone six o'clock on the button so I'll call to order this July 1st meeting of Lancaster City Council committees mr. Harris would you please
call the roll of members this evening yes madam president mr. men mr. Roya here mr. Glees here mr. Hirsch here here councillors Ahmed and Craig are excused
this evening a few reminders for everyone at the top of the meeting I asked that you please silence your phones and devices if you haven't done so already please know that this meeting and its participants are being recorded tonight we have meetings of committees of counsel there are no general public comment periods during this meeting however committee chairs will call for comments from the public on legislative items which are bills and resolutions comments are limited to three minutes per speaker and must begin with your name and block of residence for the meeting record counselors um first of all if there's an issue with the mic we can switch it out with another one that's over there okay um mayor would you switch one yes thank you thank you for bearing with us through technical difficulties perfect uh counselors will begin before the committees with the approval of the june 2nd 2025 committee meeting minutes motion to approve say again i have a motion and a second any council discussion
on the minutes all right mr harris would you call the vote on that mr roya aye mr cleese aye
miss diaz aye mr hirsch aye i'm president becky aye thank you all right we begin tonight with
the personnel committee councillor clicks thank you madam president the personal committee has four items on the agenda for tonight and all four items are nominations to for reappointment to the fire code board appeals and the nominees are Danny's Park Kenneth Barton Lloyd Henry and Jim Duncan and they currently serve on the board and they have expressed their willingness to be reappointed I'll open up for questions or comments from other members of the committees and council council just to make
a note that for reappointments we typically don't ask the the folks to come before council is that
correct yes correct thank you and thank you to them for serving any comments or questions from the public hearing none so i'll make a motion to move those nominations to our next council meeting second all in favor aye aye madam president that concludes the personal committee thank you very
much council cleeks we'll now move to the finance committee uh council arroyo thank you council
president uh we have three items on the agenda for this evening first is administration resolution number 48 2025 which is authorizing the disposal of public works vehicles and i believe uh sorry director campbell is here to speak on that resolution good evening council good evening
director campbell good evening good evening so we're very pleased to be able to bring this presentation to you it's partly asking for the the disposition of these vehicles through auction but also to give you a little bit of an update of the status of the vehicle of the fleet vehicle program so next slide please the resolutions is asking to authorize the disposal and acquisition of vehicles for DPW the resolution overview is such that we're disposing of vehicles by auction we want to dispose of six vehicles as per the on the list of by exhibit a that are no longer planned to be of service the trade-in of vehicles of 14 vehicles for other for other vehicles to be acquired by sale or lease and 11 vehicles to be rolled into new leases at best price the estimated value the council estimates that the value of vehicles to be sold to be in excess of two thousand dollars each and the authorization to proper official of to proffer officials of the city of lancaster authorized to sell and trade in the vehicles all officials are also authorized to take necessary to accomplish the purpose of the resolution next slide thank you the progress just as an update the progress of the fleet management program is as follows we have as you know entered into a contract with Enterprise fleet management which tracks equity in each vehicle and recommends replacement when our equity is at highest so it's a best management practice the we have been so far in the approximately 14 to 16 months that the contract has been in place to reduce the fleet from 251 to 239 vehicles or reduce it by 12 vehicles it all it gives us the opportunity to look at a fleet sharing model which we have implemented in part here at City Hall for and it allows us opportunities for further reductions based on usage at this moment we have approximately 12 vehicles that are in full-time use and an additional for four vehicles that are not in full-time use we believe that we can reduce the fleet share by that for but we're waiting for a little bit more data to confirm what this what the enterprise fleet management program allows us to do is to monitor usage as well as where the vehicle goes how fast it's being used if is it violating traffic laws things like that it also this program may also allow us further reduction in Police Bureau vehicles as possible next some of the other metrics of the fleet management program we have saved 81,000 in with the enterprise enterprise fleet management of ordering of 27 vehicles and maintenance in the first year so most of these are its statistics of the first 12 months of the of the contract um first year of the program 154 service is recorded with in-house auto integrate program which is the program that monitors the the con the condition it's kind of like the the uh equipment the equipment flag on your vehicle it lets us know when there's something going wrong that it needs to be attended to uh it allowed for the resale we sold 57 city-owned vehicles with $362,000 worth of equity slash trade-in value rolled into the new leases. Now, that may sound like it's just a direct savings. But basically, it allows us to leverage the funds and the value of the equity in the vehicles to acquire better performing vehicles, stronger vehicles, more modern vehicles where it's appropriate. We don't go for modern just for the sake of being modern. We go for modern only if it is in our best interest. In terms of resale, the leased unit generated $15,000. One leased unit generated $15,000 and was sold at 8% above the industry, meaning $3,152 back to the city or approximately a 20% benefit. That is one of the metrics that we're looking to continually repeat. It allows us to look at each of the vehicles in that kind of a context. Philanthropy partnerships, the Lancaster City Police Foundation received a $2,500 grant from Enterprise Foundation, and many of the metrics above contribute to the cost per unit decreasing by a little bit more than 20%, down to 44 cents per mile versus approximately 56 cents per mile just last year okay the again we don't have metrics we have okay thank you for
bearing with us I know we're work we're work we're still exploring these it
might be that let's try that's okay we'll figure it out once and once we get it exactly then we'll get a whole new system once we figure it out so again we have only anecdotal information from years previous to 2024 2024 but the average miles per gallon for the current vehicles in our fleet is approximately 25 mile miles per gallon the approximately the vehicle age has decreased in the in this last year alone from 6.5 years to 5.7 years meaning that But by being able to leverage the vehicles at their prime, we have better, younger vehicles. The fleet value of the 250 vehicles monitored by Enterprise is approximately $4.3 million. And the Geotab telematics enrollment, which is part of the technology that tracks this information, is for the 250 vehicles, tracks location of the vehicles, so we know where vehicles are 24 7 365 speed aggressive driving etc this is very important as we monitor and try to determine what appropriate policies for enforcement as well as for utilize utilization of vehicles is and it also contributes to our increased intention to have more fleet share rather than fleet do specific fleet for for city uses next at the last slide so just a quick summary of the auction and trade in details we're looking at auctioning six vehicles to be sold via the via gov deals which is the means by which we can work with the local auction houses whenever the vehicles are appropriate and get the best price trade in a 14 vehicles to be traded for new acquisitions 11 vehicles to be rolled into new leases and the replacement process in terms of explanation of timelines and next steps auction as replacement vehicles arrive so we would not be eliminating vehicles before we have the replacement and the auctions are perpetual they they they're not just once or twice a year they're often every weekend The old units get decommissioned and readied for sale, which allows us to, again, maximize the price that they can be sold at. And auctions are ongoing online, and Enterprise sells via the auto auctions. So the request, again, is to be able to auction those six vehicles and to be able to trade in the 14 vehicles for new acquisitions, as well as 11 vehicles to be rolled into new
thank you director Campbell I don't have any questions or comments are there any questions or comments from the committee or full council councillor Diaz if I may
regarding the cars what make and models are they there's a there's is a an exhibit a which has a list of each of the vehicles I'm not sure if you guys have that it should have been with the we do yeah so the six to be auctioned or the top there's another grouping of 14 which are the ones for the trading for new acquisitions there make model in year and then the eleven vehicles to be rolled into new leases are the following eleven group of eleven were you able to
find it for some reason it's not downloading for me but I'll look for it
thank you I do have a hard council president as you're looking for that
dr campbell i'm looking at the exhibit a and i just so maybe maybe i just need to kind of conceptualize we're talking about fleet management because some of the vehicles in the first list are things like dump trucks and sweepers and gators and so is enterprise fleet management also managing our fleet of those sort of specialty vehicles as well it's a very good question they
are not managing that fleet however they are the ones who would be selling at auction any of those fleet that we do have understood thank you for that clarification any of the
counselor colleagues thank you consulate Jimmy the consular way thank you and there you can but what is the process for determining a public vehicle is ready for disposal what what we have it's a very good question what
we have done is the contract for enterprise allows us to have assessed basically done a facility assessment of the condition of all the vehicles that they are managing the 250 vehicles that they are managing by age by condition by crash history by a variety of other things that that may determine what its value is and then compare that via a variety of other metrics with what the market will bear so it's we're looking at what can our vehicles in our particular situation in order for us to determine whether we sell them or not I'm sorry touching this thing in order to sell them at an appropriate level or not if for instance a vehicle I think it just might be the speaker if it is older but in a still good shape that would allow us to there's this kind of a calculus that would indicate whether it's and it's at its optimum for equity for for selling it to get the benefit of its equity or not similarly if it's a younger vehicle but it has been in a crash and has had been plagued by lemon issues by problems with it with the vehicle that would indicate that it would be ready to be sold earlier than later and who is involved in that decision it's primarily enterprise they are an industry leader in this kind of work and we have when we did the when we did the competitive solicitation we were looking at several different firms on a national level and they came in giving us the best metrics with a dashboard that we are able to use and have access to the data on a vehicle by vehicle basis daily at any way that we like so we've got the best what we believe is the best value for the proposal in that competitive proposing period
thank you director thank you counselor yeah thank you any additional questions or comments
from council any questions from the public yes i do thank you tony dastra 700 block new holland avenue i i just really need to express the frustration at the audio for a moment because i'm sitting there and i understand i'm not frustrated any individual here i know it's stuff to work through but it's not a laughing matter these sort of issues if they carry through to the live stream or the difference between someone tuning in to engage themselves civically and educate themselves and not so i just need to say that and leave it there um the only question i have is i mean we've already made changes to certain other uh processes in the city regarding the sale of property um has there been any investigation as to whether these vehicles could be used for local nonprofit needs because while i respect getting the highest dollar value for these things sometimes the greatest return comes from empowering our community organizations
thank you for that question we did not look at alternate uses of the vehicles partly because many of them are very unique vehicles they're for specific uses or specific have specific characteristics and that would mitigate our ability to to financially benefit from them it does not it does not reduce the value that they might have had for other purposes but it does increase the amount of effort and the overhead to be able to manage the disposition of those vehicles in a non-competitive setting we would be looking at several different types of solicitation to be able to make those available as well as the hands-on efforts of of managing such transfers all right thank you director campbell
with that um i will motion to move admin resolution number 48 2025 to full council all those in favor aye move on to thank you director campbell counselor can i just make
a note i want to just ensure council and members of the public in the room that we have been told that the live stream is not affected by the popping noises that we're hearing it's coming in through the speaker in the room and so the audio feed is coming in separately
through streaming thank you thank you council president next item on the agenda is resolution number 49 2025 which is authorizing a funding project uh for uh it's listed on the agenda as lancaster industrial development authority on behalf of luther care um it is actually the lancaster munis municipal authority um on behalf of luther care um and we have representatives from the municipal authority here we have oh thank you let me come on up good evening good evening
is this on yeah yes okay my name is aaron hollis i am solicitor for lancaster municipal authority and we are requesting approval for a tax exempt financing for luther care it's for 26 million dollars for acquisition and development of 37 new homes and their property and lidets as well as other capital improvements this is uh conduit financing uh this is not an obligation of the city this would be coming from a lender langstrom municipal authority's name will be on it but will not have direct obligation on these the notes for this this is a project in Lidditz we are also seeking approval in Lidditz Borough Warwick Township and Columbia Borough Lancaster Municipal Authority was approved under the city and we also under the code require approval from Lancaster City have we also have a representative of Luther care if you have any questions about the project thank you
similar resolution came before Council maybe a year ago or as far as on behalf the Lancaster Municipal Authority and as I think one of the biggest questions was does this obligate the city to any financial obligation and it doesn't it
does not no it has no direct obligation to the city and even Lancaster Municipal Authority has no direct obligation for this it is through the documents it is a note issue through Lancaster Municipal Authority but has no
direct obligation thank you open up the open up for any questions or comments from the committee or full council any questions from the public thank you thank you yeah with that I will motion to move resolution number 49 2025 to full council motion in a second all those in favor aye great next on the agenda for the Finance Committee we have a report on the earned income tax exemption I'll invite director Campbell to the table good evening director
Campbell thank you for requesting this I think counselor Hirsch requested this report this evening I'm gonna provide some information regarding a possible earned income tax exemption for lower income residents and we have put together a few considerations for you as well as some some data to show you I'm pausing until he gets the presentation up here so before we start I would like to add just a small caveat we've done quite a bit of research on this I hope you'll see that through some of these considerations however I do want to say we haven't taken a thorough dive into any of the particular considerations so the presentation tonight is estimates from what we've learned these estimates will not be exact and they will require further work depending on how council decides to pursue next steps we'll move into further considerations for the options based on on your on your proposals we tried to balance staff time for the purpose of the initial report knowing that this is the first step in the process next slide so tonight's agenda it's a short section so this isn't going to be a long report but there's five different short sections we'll give a quick overview of earned income tax review some of the data from that we'll bring some considerations forward for you to think about as you're making decisions on how to move forward we'll look at some financial estimates we'll have some potential alternatives in here as well and then we'll talk about next steps next slide please so before we dive into the exemption we thought we would give a review of what the earned income tax actually is we've been talking about this quite a bit during the home rule process so the earned income tax or EIT you'll see it referred to as EIT up here is a tax paid on income earned by anyone who lives in the city so the current rate paid by city residents is 1.1 percent of their income generally the state maximum percentage is 0.6 percent but the home rule charter allows municipalities to go higher than that and so the 1.1 was voted on with the budget as of January 1st because of the Home Rule Charter this is the city's portion of the earned income tax the school district also collects an earned income tax and they currently collect 0.5% so the total earned income tax that the city residents pay is 1.6% earned income tax is only paid on income earned so it's not paid on Social Security income so that means that many retired individuals would not be paying the earned income tax next slide please all right so an earned income tax exemption this can be determined for income earners making less than a certain amount the state sets the maximum income earned for the exception at $12,000 and we believe that this is the ceiling regardless of home status for any municipality in Pennsylvania we currently don't have an exemption for the earned income tax and this is what we're going to explore a little bit this evening I will just note there's another tax the local service tax this is collected from anyone who works in the city regardless of where they live we do offer an exemption for that tax the if the income is under twelve thousand and again that's the state maximum so we want to give a few data points for you from across the state so from what we found there's currently we think 36 municipalities in Pennsylvania that are currently offering an earned income tax exemption this is actually 1.4 percent of all municipalities in Pennsylvania so there's about 2,600 municipalities across the state this is according to the DCED website and we discovered that this number might actually still be a little high one of the municipalities shown to be giving an earned income tax exemption is in Lancaster County so we actually reached out to them and they did they were not aware that they were offering this exemption so so that but this is what the DCD list is showing at this time so of the 36 municipalities 11 of them have a population over 10,000 and there's one Ben Salem which is close to Philadelphia that's slightly larger than Lancaster City with a population just over 60,000 all of the other municipalities are smaller than Lancaster so we would be one of the largest to have this exemption about two-thirds of the municipalities have a population under 10,000 the smallest municipality offering this is made up of 422 people so it's quite small and none of the 36 municipalities have an exemption that's above 12,000 they actually range anywhere from 200 up to 12 000 which was interesting to see all right next slide please so some considerations to think about as we were reviewing this our solicitor Mr. Hanwerger reviewed some of the exemption level requirements and as I mentioned we were conferring with some outside consultants as well and they believe that we cannot go above that twelve thousand dollar income level regardless of the home rule status as I stated earlier so I'm focusing data tonight on what it it would look like for Lancaster to do this at the twelve thousand dollar level additionally we met with the Lancaster County Tax Collection Bureau and they actually provided quite a bit of data for us to look into which was really helpful for this process so they also went out and talked to a second tax collection agent agency that works with the large portion of the 36 municipalities who are currently doing the exemptions and these are some considerations that come from both the Lancaster County Tax Collection Bureau as well as this other Tax Collection Bureau one of them is that we would want to ensure that there's some provision that this would only be eligible for anyone who has lived in the city for the full calendar year otherwise someone who has a higher income might move into the city very late in the year but still receive the exemption because of that income threshold the exemption must work on a refund basis this is required for two reasons one is we're not able to determine who is making less than the threshold until after taxes are filed so residents would still need to pay the tax throughout the year and then be refunded after they file the tax the second is actually more important because the school district receives a portion of the tax and that portion is not exempt they would still need to pay that portion so the tax is collected at the full percentage and then divided between the city and the school district so it can't be withheld throughout the year residents would need to file the taxes by the tax deadline in order to have the Tax Collection Bureau have capacity to process the refunds and I I'm going to mention a bit later that the Tax Collection Bureau would be the ones processing these these refunds the the Bureau estimates that only about 50% of residents actually file taxes timely at this point that said if and if there is an exemption as an option we would anticipate that more taxpayers would be filing in a more timely manner and then finally in discussion with the Tax Collection Bureau we've also determined that really the only reasonable option to have these exceptions process would be to have them do the do the processing for us as we talked about it because of some of the confidential taxpayer information it'd be very difficult to get the information needed to city staff or other issues or other entities to actually issue the refunds but they have agreed that they could do the work for a fee so that was that was a helpful step to determine all right next slide please okay so some of the numbers this is where it may get a little complicated so I'm gonna try to keep this as try to explain it as best I can so these numbers are estimates using 2024 numbers we had to make some educated assumptions as I mentioned earlier we don't have historic trends to show us you know this type of exemptions shift at this point so we're using some some estimations here based on the 2024 percentage of tax filers the city would receive approximately 130,000 in income from about 3,600 taxpayers making 12,000 or annually this is if if taxpayers were filing at the at the rate that they are typically filing now we're estimating that approximately 20% more taxpayers would file with the incentive of a refund so that would equal about two hundred fifty eight thousand with a total of about forty six hundred individual taxpayers so the dollar amount as you can see almost doubles from the hundred and thirty thousand to the two hundred fifty eight thousand with this additional filing and that's because the the taxpayers earning closer to twelve thousand would likely be the ones to file at a greater number or this is what we're anticipating so we would anticipate that there would be higher amounts coming in for that and therefore for the purposes of this estimate we're using that two hundred fifty eight thousand we're considering that two 258,000 to be kind of the lost revenue for the city I'm putting that in quotes but that would be technically what would no longer be available as tax revenue so this is where it may get a little complicated but of this 258,000 we now need to consider a non-resident earned income tax the non-resident earned income tax applies to anyone living in the city but working in a different municipality so residents are charged one earned income tax I mentioned that it's together the city and the school district this earned income tax will first go to the municipality in which they live if the municipality that the resident lives in decides not to charge an earned income tax or if it's refunded the municipality that they're working in has a right to collect a non-resident tax so we we actually collect a non-resident earned income tax from this as well and I'll give you just it's it's very a very small amount in June our total earned income tax that came in was five hundred and twenty six thousand non-resident of that the non-resident portion was five thousand so it's about one percent so back to this example if someone lives in the city but works in Mannheim Township Mannheim Township would generally not collect the non-resident tax because the city gets the tax first before the outside municipality would however if the resident living in Lancaster City gets an exemption to that 1.1 percent rate in essence this means that the resident has not yet paid an earned income tax so then Mannheim Township would be eligible to receive their non-resident tax at their rate which at this point is 0.6 percent because they don't have that exemption they would receive that funding and then the resident would receive a refund of 0.5 instead of the full 1.1% so based on what the Tax Collection Bureau could obtain in the last couple of weeks looking at you know residents living in the city and working outside it looks like approximately 117,000 of the 258,000 would be paid to other municipalities the taxpayer would then receive about 141,000 as a refund and the average refund would be about $42 per resident and then additionally we would we would be paying a fee to the Tax Collection Bureau for the work it would be about ten dollars per filing so about forty seven thousand dollars we're figuring so the city's total outlay with the revenue reduction and the expenses for processing would be approximately three hundred and four thousand and a hundred and forty one thousand of that so about forty six percent less than half of the total outlay would actually go back to the taxpayers that's a lot of numbers so the next slide is gonna just graph it out a little bit for us this is showing on the left-hand side what would go to the other municipalities the processing fee and then the refund to residents and so you can kind of see regardless of what what level the numbers are you can kind of see the percentages they're a little bit better as well all right next slide I want to give some potential alternatives to this ultimately council needs to decide about pursuing an exemption however given that potentially more than half of the total financial outlay may not actually end up going back to the taxpayers we wanted to offer some other options so one to consider would be an application process this wouldn't necessarily eliminate the the the pieces that are not going to the taxpayers but it could lower the processing because there might not be quite as many applications that would be coming through this piece we haven't researched fully yet again so that we would need some further consideration if we would want to go that route we could also consider allocating you know basically the same portion that would have been refunded or would have been our total outlay to a program that we might already be doing that that could be helping low-income individuals so a couple of them are listed here the critical repair fund we've talked about that often at council that's that specifically supports low-income individuals in the city and it would mean that all of the funds would actually be kept to be used for city residents we could also consider allocating some to the Lancaster Water Assistance Program that's the program that is offered through CAP for utility support for lower-income households and we could designate this is for all of the households that the program is set up for all of the households that we serve with our utilities but we could designate this portion just for in-city residents and then we could explore new programs if you would like to help lower income households we could research next steps on those as well last slide so ultimately we'll need direction from council on what you'd like to have more information on as I mentioned these are all estimates at this point so once we have a general direction we can work on more concrete information to provide and once the focus or direction is determined we will account for those costs in the budget you know we're currently working on the budget we'll have a final draft hopefully completed by the last week in September so we'd want to at least include some estimates
based on the approach by then thank you director Campbell very informative and I appreciate all the hard work in doing the research to answer this question I know this is something that's come up before council and a lot of counselors interests over the last few months since the passing of the new home rule charter so I appreciate providing some of this clarity I know for me personally the the need to consider the non-resident earned income tax was relatively new information that's something that I was not aware of that would get unlocked for lack of a better term if we were to provide an exemption on the earned income tax it's also pretty startling to think that it would actually cost us more money to provide the exemption than would actually be collected so if am i write anything in noting the $258,000 that would have been collected and then refunded as a as a exemption would actually cost the city in total three hundred and four thousand yeah so definitely something to consider I do appreciate the alternatives as well I think when we look at the problem that we're trying to solve with the exemption it was providing relief to low-income taxpayers here in the city of Lancaster and thinking about other potential allocations other funds or other programs that offer that direct impact I know I'll speak for myself sounds a lot more appealing knowing that the residents that needed the most will receive the full dollar of that impact right here in the city of Lancaster rather than a portion so just some of my thoughts but happy to open up to the committee or full council thank you very
much director Campbell for the thorough research and part of the reason I had asked for this report is just knowing that it wasn't just as simple as you know okay what's the budgetary impact if we say you know on this increment of tax you don't have to pay tax that there is a lot of logistical considerations into doing an exemption and having heard a lot of the logistical considerations you've given us a lot to think about that's for sure and I don't want to say I'm closing the door but it definitely sounds like kind of a lot of headache for not necessarily a lot of return and I'm definitely I've grown a little colder to this idea than maybe I came in to this meeting that said you know I I agree, Councilor Arroyo, I think any ways that we can return tax dollars to low income residents and to residents, period, overall, I think is something that we should always be looking into. And I'll just go back, I'll finish my comments just by saying I really appreciated the presentation we just got on the fleet management. kind of I think an example of like where we can return a lot of value to tax payers or at least it really I think show had shown itself in that presentation so I really admire the work that the city has done with that so like I said I will have to think about all of this me personally you've done a lot given us a lot to think about so thank you very much again for the thorough research and all the great information you were able to gather Thank You
councillor Hirsch any other questions or comments from council members
Councillor Arroyo thank you thank you for the presentation and I know it was a lot of work to put together and I know that further exploration will require a lot more I appreciate I want to echo the sentiments that I think the giving funds to other municipalities aspect of this was eye-opening and not something that I'm particularly interested in doing as a steward of the tax dollars the city of Lancaster but I do appreciate the alternatives that are presented and I think that we can this is people often talk about getting creative and this is one way where we could do that and so this is a start and there may be some other ideas speaking as your council president I'm very open to hear those from councillors if you have other thoughts whether they are on the list of what's here or other ideas on how we can make a better investment for our lowest income residents just and out of curiosity I'm trying to do the math and it's not necessarily my strongest suit but a person who makes eleven thousand nine hundred and ninety nine dollars how much is that really at the current tax rate is that they're paying could someone do that okay and so they may get half of that back in the end instead of the full amount if we go through this process for a full year for a full year okay thank you I appreciate the can
come appreciate confirming my math if they don't live and work in this if they live and work in the city they would get right but if they live outside of the
city that could be as little as half 46 percent thank you any additional
questions or comments from council great well we have a lot to process and to think about but appreciate the report director Campbell thank you there's no action being taken on this so since it's just a report from council there'll be no public comment with that I'll close the Finance Committee comes president
Thank You council rail I'm actually gonna turn it right back to you our next committee is community planning councillor Craig is absent this evening so councillor Roya if you would chair this one this evening Thank You
council president there are two items on the community planning committee this evening the first admit first is administration resolution number 50 2025 which is authorizing a ground lease agreement for a sunnyside environmental center and i believe mr hand workers here
there you go good evening i figured if we sent you a hundred pages of legal documents i probably should well i i appreciate that i sent you 100 pages of legal documents and i appreciated the
executive summary as well so thank you it should be on with the red light there so good as you
recall you've already actually essentially approved this in a previous resolution but given the fact that this is a 99 year lease given the fact that this is going to have impact on generations of lancaster residents hereafter it's it's it's important for city council to have the documents and approve them before signature the executive summary i sent you the summary prepared essentially covers the primary points of the transaction the documents which are an agreement to enter into ground lease and then subsequently ground lease and the reason they're broken out into two parts is there's a there's a lengthy due process process for lack of a better word that that partners from environmental stewardship will need to go through in designing a building that will meet the world-class standards that they've committed to that will provide the programming and impetus for residents of the city of lancaster that will be in conjunction with the with the preserve that's going to take at least 18 months if not longer just to do some basic design and research and then they've got to go through land development process it is a lengthy process there hasn't been any testing done on land yet so all of those things have to happen which are fairly normal in a land development transaction when somebody buys land the unique nature of this transaction is that we are dividing title right so title as you get it when you buy a house you get what's called fee simple title you own 100 of all the interest in that property subject to any rights that say utility might have for running electric that would be an easement the difference here is that we're not giving that interest to pes rather we're giving them a 99-year ground lease so essentially we're leasing the land to them and they get that land to do to control build on as set forth in these documents and at the end of the 99-year lease it terminates unless it's extended by the parties So that's a somewhat different type of transaction than what we were normally doing. We'd sell a house, buy a house, or donate that. The rationale for that is that was part of the original transaction. It was so that the city is continuing to maintain its asset, which is a little over eight acres, almost nine acres, that the environmental center will sit on and be utilized. Once the due diligence is done and they're ready to move forward, that's when the ground leases signed the two documents work together obviously one governs what happens prior to actually signing the lease and then the lease governs what happens for the next 99 years thereafter i think most of the salient points were in the legal memo confidential legal memo i provided to you but it's an as is say as is transaction there's no net cost to the city in other words all costs of operating the land are borne by partners for environmental stewardship there are obligations that that were included in the letter of intent that are maintained in these documents that require them to build the building in a state of an art manner and over the 18 months city staff has been convinced that in fact you will be very pleased with what ends up happening i think their plans are to make this one of the 35th building of its type in the world not just the country but the world so very high aspirations for this building and for its uses to benefiting residents directly through programming there's multiple reporting on the programming that's required annually and then programming plans need to be updated every five years so that there's a constant communication with the city staff and with city council through the course of the 99-year lease as to making sure that the program is consistent with the preserve which the city will be responsible for creating and maintaining that will be in and around the eight acres that the environmental center sits on based on the legislative calendar this matter has been asked to be moved to council's agenda for august 12th one of the things i would suggest for you is that if you have questions for me regarding any of the specifics of the language in these documents it gives you plenty of time to to get them in for us to get answers back to you as well and i'm happy to do so and again we're really pleased to be bringing this to you this evening at this point after approximately 18 months of work hard work by by the high foundation and partners for environmental stewardship they've already started their work in anticipation of this going forward they've made that commitment even though they don't have a signed deal yet um and uh we're really excited about what this is going to do for the city and it's consistent obviously with the comprehensive plan that was recently adopted and the previous resolution that you adopted in december right thank you um yeah i uh very
excited about this project and to your point um very much in alignment with uh the comprehensive plan um and very excited to hear about the standard of the build as well as uh um just the level of standard that's going to be exciting so um i do know we have uh members of the high foundation and partners of environmental stewardship here yeah they're here to observe okay great um so uh with that any questions or comments from uh the committee or full council
councilor council president mr hanberger thank you so much for the summary and for everyone's work on the lease agreement i know it's it's an intense and long document and i just wanted to say that i appreciate that it has uh continued to capture the um the the pieces of the letter intent that were originally included that were originally improved by approved by council that were so important to us in this in this particular agreement including the build standards but also the resident program resident engagement and programming to benefit the residents and having that continuous reporting in there is incredibly important and i think that um i just wanted to say to council and in general that i think that this is a model for ways that we need to build that into anything that happens in our community because we can build that in from the beginning and i feel like we've done that here so i feel really good about that so thank you
thank you council president any additional questions or comments from council
my question is just around the I guess I just want to make sure I understand correctly what I read there's quite a lot of you know reading to do but in particular in the agreements surrounding the water line as I read it it read as though that partners for environmental stewardship would be required to allow for an easement for a water line to go through the preserve and I guess is there any legal protection they would have in regards to if I guess we're talking about a preserve and then building a water line through it as their legal protection over over the preserve piece of the property if that makes sense does my question make sense so I mean keep in
mind the water line would be something that the city is proposing to build so would obviously have done the homework to determine whether it would have any damage to its property which is the preserve there are areas in the peninsula that may need to ultimately be served by water and we as a municipal authority regulated by the puc very well may have obligations to actually provide water to them so we've left open the options and abilities to run a line as long as it doesn't interfere with the environmental center itself that's what they've agreed to allow us to do it goes across their portion of the property whether that came across the portions of the preserve there's no particular route that's been determined yet obviously this is all about protecting the the abilities in the future to maximize the site for all which is a part of what the master site plan will help us do as well
so if i hear you correctly you're saying that it's in part to protect the the possibility that the city you know if someone is seeking to tap into water service that the city is able to run a line where need be but then also does provide the partners for environmental stewardship some protection their building is absolutely protected okay that's correct okay and it was also helpful to hear that there hasn't necessarily been a particular route picked yet either okay okay i think that that answers my question on that thank you thank you councillor hirsch any additional
questions or comments uh my last question um just to confirm uh any motion to move this forward would be for the august 12th uh council meeting correct great thank you um great with that uh i will motion to move administration resolution number 50 2025 uh to the august 12th council meeting second are those in favor aye aye great thank you thank you next we'll move to resolution number 51 2025 authorizing an amendment of the official sewage facilities plan to include the
swan hotel project good evening turning around so many times good evening uh lauren finn senior planner for the city this um this sewer planning module is for the swan hotel redevelopment so it's located at 101 south queen street we've been looking forward to the redevelopment of of this hotel for a while it's an interesting piece in that it actually doesn't have to go through a full land development because they're not changing so much to the footprint of the building so they're just going through kind of an abbreviated process in land development and the process with the county as well for the sewer module thank you thanks any questions or comments from council
any from the public uh with that i'll motion to move resolution number 51 2025 to the next full council meeting so move are those in favor aye aye great uh council president that concludes the
community planning committee thank you council arroyo uh next we have the public works committee
council hirsch thank you council president um we have two items on the public works committee of meeting or agenda the first of which is resolution 52 which is authorizing a grant for the eastbound connector this is the bicycle path that is going towards the GOAT path east kind of in and around in and around Lincoln Middle School and the hope is to get that to ultimately connect to the GOAT path I see director Campbell coming up so I'll let him take over thank you very much
again for this opportunity this is we're submitting this a little bit early because we're making a request for to make this application to the multimodal transportation fund we had previously made an application for significantly more money and granted only two hundred thousand dollars which we now have but interestingly we've been invited to make another application we do not yet know what yet what the likely amount is part of the challenge with this particular site is that it is three municipalities it is not only the city of Lancaster but it is Mannheim Township and it's Lancaster Township and although we have a lot of participation from from both municipalities there each each municipality has a varying level of financial capability this is the opportunity to to link pedestrian way a better vehicular way and the active transportation network from the boroughs the new boroughs school campus to the Lancaster to the McCaskey campus as well we have enough we currently have money in hand to do the design work and to continue some of the the logistics of working with the different municipalities and some of some low-hanging fruit work to be installed before the end of 2027 but the but we expect that the major construction would be taking place as late as 2031 if we are successful with this application which again we're hopefully coming back to you around for the June 22nd as the first opportunity to tell you what the cost is because we're still awaiting guidance from mta mtf on how much they would likely be we would likely be eligible for but that would allow us to reduce the amount of money that's coming from our from our 2025 bond at in the short term and that's money that could be used for other purposes
thank you very much director Campbell that's helpful yes and thank you for that explanation as well as to why there's not an amount put there yet appreciate that they're willing to work with you on that and provide some guidance so I will open and to be clear this is this resolution grants permission to apply for the grant so with that I will open up comment to
members of the Public Works Committee or full council I can't recall if it's the resolutions accepting awards or if it's the application that mentions if there's a commitment or a match is there a commitment or a match with these MTF
funds director Campbell that would be a question for the next meeting thank you so much for providing that. I'm assuming that there is but I
don't want to. I thought typically so. Okay. Thank you
Council President. Councilor Clicks. Thank you Councilor
Hodge. Director Campbell, could you tell us some of the benefits
of this project for the community? Oh, yes. This is a very interesting site because it is the nexus of Rank Mill Road and the Walnut Street but also the what's the one that goes straight over towards the operation center is Rank Mill Pleasure or Graftown so there's a lot of students from all three municipalities that will be traversing in this area because of the extensive nature of the Lancaster of the McCaskey campus as well as the new boroughs elementary school which is under construction right now that particular roadway groftown road in particular has excessive speeds right now partly because of people coming off of off of chestnut street and flying into that particular curve there's there's nothing that slows the traffic in that particular area this is an opportunity for us to use our best management practices that are that are similar to what you've seen in other parts of the city we use for safe streets for all and the vision zero program to be able to reduce the speeds in that particular stretch of the city as well as to augment the active transportation network so this is one of the key intersections where bikes bike lanes and bike access can be provided as well going up broad street as you know there's the chesapeake broad intersection that's that's under that will be underway in 2026 that provides a loop for people to come from southwest through southeast up to the mccaskey campus but also this is this is one of the last connectors to the the county-wide active transportation network which connects us to the goat path among other things so we're very much looking forward to the ultimate design and resolution to be a much more pedestrian friendly area with slower speeds slower traffic coming in this particular area and controls that a couple of things that are being considered are not just full intersections but also stoplights possible intersection as well again we're that's still part of the study but what we need to make sure is that students from the boroughs community in Lancaster Township can safely cross this intersection in this series of streets to the to the McCaskey campus and vice-versa so I think there's a lot of benefits to this particular area thank
you thank you thank you thank you thank you
thank you council cleek's thank you so 70 30 grand okay thank you are there any
other questions or comments from council hearing none I will make a motion to move this to our meeting of council on July 22nd so you all those in favor aye and our next resolution is a resolution recognizing Parks and Recreation Month resolution 53 forgive me I'm pulling up the resolution here just the resolution talks quite a bit about our partnership with the Lancaster Rec Commission and the offering of programming from our parks and recognizes you know the great partnership that we've had with them for decades and also recognizes the benefit that parks have in our community and thankfully you know we've been putting a lot of effort into renovating her parks so we recognize the value that they provide to the city so you know I won't read the resolution out loud but that's kind of some of the things that it talks about I know last year we had Heather DJ from the Lancaster rec give a presentation don't know if that's anything like that's forthcoming this year but still do you think it's really important to recognize both the value that the parks add to our city that the programming ads to our city and then also all of the all of the staff that makes that happen and all of the public work staff that keeps our park clean I'm really grateful for them so I don't really have much else to say on this particular resolution but I want to make sure that we recognize all the people that work hard to bring that benefit to our community so I will open it up to public works committee or full council if they have any comment okay hearing none I will make a motion to move this to our full meeting of council on July 8th so all those in favor aye that concludes yes I exercised discretion and did not feel it merited public comment at this moment as a reminder committee public comment is not a requirement that's all I really have to say on that
Thank You counselor includes public works committee appreciate it all right councillors we don't have any committee of the whole items this evening the last item on our agenda is the clerk's report mr. Harris confirming that you've submitted that to the council in writing thank you very much then reached the end of our agendas I will hear a motion to adjourn motion to adjourn second motion and a second all in favor aye thank you we're adjourned